Let me ask you a question
我问你一个问题
You spent 200 yuan on an AI membership
你花了200块买了一个AI会员
Used it for a month
用了一个月
And realized you barely use it at all
发现自己根本不怎么用
It's about to expire
到期了
Will you renew
你会续费吗
If you say no
如果你说不会
Then let me ask you this
那我再问你
Why have you been renewing it for six months straight
为什么你已经连续续了半年了
You're not alone in this
这不是你一个人的问题
Over 300 million people worldwide are paying for subscriptions they barely use
全球有超过3亿人正在为自己不怎么用的订阅服务付费
Netflix
Netflix
ChatGPT
ChatGPT
Spotify
Spotify
All kinds of cloud storage
各种云存储
Your bank card is bleeding money every month
你的银行卡每个月在自动失血
And you don't even notice
你甚至都忘了
Let me do the math for you
我给你算笔账
How many subscriptions do you have on your phone right now
你手机里现在有几个订阅服务
Five
5个
Eight
8个
Average 30 yuan per month each
平均每个30块一个月
Five means 150 a month
5个就是150
That's 1800 yuan a year
一年下来1800块
But the ones you actually open every week
但你真正每周打开的
Are probably just one or two
可能就1到2个
The other three
剩下那3个
You're just giving money away every month
你每个月在白白送钱
1800 yuan isn't much
1800块不多
But you're buying something every year
但这是你每年在买一个东西
The illusion that you'll definitely use it someday
买一个我总觉得以后会用到的幻觉
Today I'm going to tell you
今天我要告诉你
There's an economic principle manipulating your brain behind all this
这背后有一个经济学原理在操控你的大脑
Understand it
搞懂它
And you can save at least a few thousand yuan every year
你每年至少能省下几千块
And this principle
而且这个原理
Doesn't just save you money
不只能帮你省钱
It can help you make the hardest decisions in your life
它能帮你做出人生中最难的那些决定
In 1985
1985年
Ohio University conducted an experiment
美国俄亥俄大学做了一个实验
When selling tickets at a theater
他们在一个剧院卖票的时候
They randomly gave discounts to some buyers
随机给一些买票的人打折
Some paid full price
有人全价买
15 yuan
15块
Some got a discount
有人折扣价
8 yuan
8块
And some only paid 2 yuan
还有人只花了2块
Then they tracked attendance for an entire season
然后他们跟踪了一整个演出季
To see who attended the most shows
看谁去看的场次最多
Guess what they found
你猜结果是什么
The people who paid 15 yuan full price
花15块全价买票的人
Attended the most shows
去看的次数最多
The ones who paid 2 yuan
花2块买的人
Actually went the least
反而经常不去
Logically
按理说
The ticket is already bought
票已经买了
No matter how much you paid
不管花多少钱
Going or not should only depend on whether you want to see it
去不去看应该只取决于你想不想看
Right
对吧
But it doesn't
但不是
The more you spend
花的钱越多
The more you feel like not going is a waste
你越觉得不去就亏了
Why do people think this way
为什么人会有这种心理
Nobel Prize winner Daniel Kahneman studied this his entire life
诺贝尔经济学奖得主丹尼尔·卡尼曼研究了一辈子这件事
He found that
他发现
The pain of losing something
人对损失的痛感
Is twice as intense as the pleasure of gaining something
是获得的快感的两倍
The happiness of finding 100 yuan
你捡到100块的开心
Is nowhere near the pain of losing 100 yuan
远远比不上丢了100块的心痛
So you don't really want to see the show
所以你不是真的想去看演出
You just can't stand the pain of having wasted money
你只是受不了白花了的痛
This is sunk cost
这就是沉没成本
The economic definition is simple
经济学的定义很简单
Costs that have already occurred
已经发生的
And cannot be recovered
无法收回的支出
Are called sunk costs
就叫沉没成本
Let me give you an example you might relate to more
我再说一个你可能更有感触的例子
You go to a buffet
你去吃自助餐
298 yuan per person
298一位
After you walk in
进去之后
What's the first thing you think
你心里想的是什么
I have to eat my money's worth
必须吃回本
So you grab all the expensive stuff
于是你拼命拿贵的
Seafood
海鲜
Steak
牛排
Sashimi
刺身
You're stuffed
吃到撑了
But you won't stop
还是不肯停
Why
为什么
I haven't eaten 298 yuan worth yet
我还没吃够298的量呢
The result
结果呢
You get acute gastroenteritis
吃出急性肠胃炎
Hospital bill is 800 yuan
去医院花了800
The 298 buffet wasn't earned back
自助餐的298没吃回来
And you lost another 800 on top
又搭进去800
When you paid that 298 yuan
你花298的时候
The money was already gone
这钱就已经没了
Whether you can eat your money's worth
你能不能吃回本
Has nothing to do with that 298 anymore
跟这298已经没关系了
What you should really do
真正该做的
Is stop when you're comfortable
是吃到舒服就停
But sunk cost won't let you stop
但沉没成本不让你停
Let me give you a more everyday example
我再给你一个更日常的例子
You spent 80 yuan on a movie ticket
你花80块买了张电影票
Watched for 20 minutes
看了20分钟
And realized the movie is terrible
发现这电影烂透了
What would you do
你会怎么做
Most people would choose
大多数人会选择
To sit through it
继续看完
What's the reason
理由是什么
I already paid for it
钱都花了
Not finishing it would be a waste
不看完就亏了
But think about it carefully
但你仔细想
That 80 yuan
那80块钱
Whether you finish watching or not
不管你看不看完
Is already spent
都已经花了
It's not coming back
它回不来了
The real question to ask is
真正该问的问题是
How do you want to spend
接下来这90分钟
The next 90 minutes more valuably
你怎么花更有价值
Keep watching a bad movie
继续看一部烂片
Or go for a walk
还是出去散个步
Read a book
看本书
Scroll on your phone for a bit
刷会儿手机
Any of these is better than sitting there suffering
哪个都比坐在那受罪强
The so-called sunk cost fallacy
所谓沉没成本谬误
Is letting money that's already spent
就是让已经花掉的钱
Hijack your future choices
绑架了你接下来的选择
Now
好
Back to the AI topic
回到AI的话题
There are so many AI subscription services it's dizzying
现在AI订阅服务多到眼花缭乱
ChatGPT
ChatGPT
Claude
Claude
Midjourney
Midjourney
Cursor
Cursor
Copilot
Copilot
Notion AI
Notion AI……
Many people impulsively sign up for several
很多人一冲动就开了好几个
Try this one
这个试试
Get that one too
那个也来一个
Auto-charged every month
每个月自动扣款
Until you forget about it
扣到你都忘了
But when you check your screen time
但你打开手机屏幕使用时间一看
You only used this tool for 15 minutes last week
上周这个工具只用了15分钟
You know you should cancel
你知道该退
But you just can't bring yourself to do it
但你就是不想退
Because there's a voice in your head saying
因为你心里有个声音在说
I've already paid for six months
我都已经交了半年了
Canceling now would be a waste
现在退不就白交了吗
Listen carefully
注意听
The money that's already sunk
已经沉没的钱
Is not within your control
不是你能控制的
But whether you keep throwing money into the water
但接下来要不要继续往水里扔钱
Is entirely up to you
是你能控制的
These two things must be separated
这两件事必须分开
And the product managers at AI companies
而AI公司的产品经理
Understand your psychology perfectly
他们非常懂你这个心理
They've designed three mechanisms specifically to lock you in
他们专门设计了三层机制来把你锁住
The first layer
第一层
Is called the annual discount
叫年付折扣
Save 40 percent with annual billing
年付省40%
You see that and think
你一看
Oh wow
哎
Saving hundreds at once
一下子省好几百
What a deal
赚了
But what is it really
但本质上是什么
It's making your sunk cost enormous all at once
是让你的沉没成本一步到位变得巨大
Once you pay the annual fee
一旦付了年费
And want to cancel midway
中途想退
Haven't I wasted the money from previous months
那我前面几个月的钱不就白花了吗
See
你看
The trap strikes again
陷阱又来了
Let me calculate for you
我给你算一下
ChatGPT Plus is 20 dollars per month
ChatGPT Plus月付20美元
Annual billing claims to save 40 percent
年付号称省40%
Looks like you save a lot
看起来一下省了好几百
But what if you only actually use it for 3 months out of the year
但如果你一年真正只用了3个月呢
You paid for 12 months
你花了全年12个月的钱
But only got 3 months of value
买了3个月的服务
Saved money
省了
You lost big time
你亏大了
The second layer
第二层
Is called data lock-in
叫数据绑定
Your chat history
你的聊天记录
The custom prompts you spent a month perfecting
你花了一个月调教出来的自定义提示词
Your usage habits
你的使用习惯
Are all stored inside
全存在里面
Switch to another tool
换一个工具
And you start from zero
意味着从零开始
This isn't a money sunk cost anymore
这不是钱的沉没成本了
This is a time and energy sunk cost
这是时间和精力的沉没成本
Which hurts even more
更痛
The third layer
第三层
Is called tiered pricing
叫阶梯定价
First let you use it for free
先免费让你用起来
Once you're used to it
等你用顺手了
Tell you that upgrading unlocks full features
告诉你升级才能解锁完整功能
You've already spent two weeks learning how to use it
你已经花了两周学会怎么用了
Not upgrading now
这时候不升级
Feels like the time spent was wasted
又觉得前面的时间白费了
Let me tell you a real story
我给你讲个真实的故事
I didn't make this up
不是我编的
Go ask in the comments
你去评论区问问
Tons of people fell for it
一堆人中招
A freelancer
有个自由职业者
Subscribed to ChatGPT
同时订阅了ChatGPT
Midjourney
Midjourney
Cursor
Cursor
Notion AI
Notion AI
Copilot
Copilot
Five AI tools
5个AI工具
Monthly membership fees alone over 700 yuan
每个月光会员费就700多块
He thought he was an AI super user
他觉得自己是AI超级用户
Very cutting edge
很前沿
Then one day he checked his screen time
结果有天他打开屏幕使用时间一看
Last week he only actually opened ChatGPT
上周实际打开的只有ChatGPT
For less than 20 minutes
用了不到20分钟
The other four
其余4个
Zero
零
700 yuan
700块
For 20 minutes of use
换了20分钟的使用
Open your subscription list right now and check
你现在打开你的订阅列表看看
How many do you have
你有几个
How many do you actually use
真心用得上的又有几个
Stack all three layers together
三层叠在一起
Money lock-in
金钱绑定
Data lock-in
数据绑定
Habit lock-in
习惯绑定
You're locked in a cycle of endless renewals
你就被锁在了一个不断续费的循环里
And you even think it's your own choice
而且你还觉得这是自己的选择
You might think
你可能觉得
It's just a few memberships
不就是几个会员嘛
Cancel them and move on
退了就退了
Not a big deal
又不是多大的事
But the truly terrifying thing about sunk cost isn't here
但沉没成本真正可怕的地方不在这
It's in the big decisions of your life
在你人生中那些大决定里
Where its impact is devastating
它的杀伤力是致命的
Let me give you three examples
我给你举三个例子
See how many you've fallen for
你看看自己中了几个
First one
第一个
Getting stuck holding losing stocks
炒股被套
You bought a stock at 10 yuan
你10块钱买了一支股票
It dropped to 6
跌到6块
All your analysis tells you
你所有的分析都告诉你
This stock has no hope
这支股票没希望了
But you just won't sell
但你就是不卖
Why
为什么
I've already lost 40 percent
我已经亏了40%了
Selling now would be too painful
现在割肉也太亏了
Let me wait a bit longer
再等等吧
Then it drops from 6 to 3
然后从6块跌到3块
From 3 to 1
从3块跌到1块
The numbers speak
数据说话
The Shanghai Stock Exchange has statistics
上交所统计过
Less than 10 percent of retail investors in A-shares are profitable long-term
A股散户长期盈利的比例不到10%
Why do so many people lose money
为什么那么多人亏
One core reason is
其中一个核心原因就是
They can't cut their losses
割不了肉
Holding losing positions
被套了不卖
Getting deeper and deeper
越套越深
The deeper they go the less they sell
越深越不卖
A vicious cycle
恶性循环
The money lost when it was at 10 yuan
那些10块钱时候亏的钱
And the money you lost afterward
和你后来继续亏的钱
Are they related
有关系吗
No
没有
They are two completely independent decisions
它们是两笔完全独立的决策
But sunk cost makes you tie them together
但沉没成本让你把它们捆在了一起
Second one
第二个
A relationship that isn't working
一段不合适的关系
You've been together for three years
在一起三年了
You know in your heart
你心里清楚
This relationship has no future
这段关系已经没有未来了
But you can't let go
但你不甘心
I've already invested three years of my youth
我已经付出了三年的青春
If I leave now
现在离开
Wasn't it all for nothing
之前不就白费了吗
The three years have already passed
三年已经过去了
Whether you stay or go
不管你走不走
They're not coming back
它都回不来
The real question is
真正的问题是
Are you willing to gamble another three years
你愿不愿意再搭上下一个三年
Third one
第三个
A dead-end job
一份没前途的工作
You've been at a company for five years
你在一家公司干了五年
No growth
没有成长
No raise
没有涨薪
No hope in sight
看不到希望
But you won't leave
但你不跳
I've already been here five years
我都干了五年了
Leaving now would be such a waste
现在走太可惜了
Let me stick it out
再熬熬吧
Maybe things will get better
也许会好的
Fourth one
第四个
A training course that isn't right for you
一个不适合的培训课
You spent 20000 yuan on a coding bootcamp
你花了两万块报了一个编程培训班
After a few classes
上了几节课
You realize you can't keep up at all
你发现自己根本跟不上
What the teacher covers doesn't match your direction
老师讲的东西跟你的方向也不搭
But you won't drop the course
但你不会退课
Why
为什么
I already paid 20000
两万块都交了
Not finishing would be a waste
不学完不就白花了
So you force yourself through three months
于是你硬着头皮上了三个月
Three months of time
三个月的时间
If you had done something else instead
如果你去做别的
Learn a skill that suits you better
学一个更适合自己的技能
Take on a project that builds experience
接一个能涨经验的项目
Or even just rest properly
甚至就是好好休息
Any of these is better than sitting through a class you don't understand
哪个不比坐在那听不懂的课上强
These four scenarios
这四个场景
Stocks
炒股
Relationships
感情
Career
职业
Education
教育
Are all driven by the same thing underneath
本质上都是同一个东西在作祟
You won't accept that past investments are unrecoverable
你不愿意承认过去的投入已经无法收回
So you try to compensate with even more investment
所以你用更多的投入去弥补
But you're not compensating
但你不是在弥补
You're doubling down on losses
你是在加码亏损
Having said all this
说了这么多
How do you break free
怎么破
I'll give you three questions
我给你三个问题
Every time you're at the crossroads of should I keep going
每次你站在要不要继续的十字路口时
Pull them out and ask yourself
拿出来问自己
First question
第一个问题
The zero-based test
「归零测试」
Imagine you're encountering this for the first time today
假设你今天才第一次遇到这件事
This stock
这支股票
This person
这个人
This job
这份工作
This AI membership
这个AI会员
Given the current situation
以现在的状态
Would you still choose it
你还会选它吗
Forget how much you've already spent
忘掉你之前花了多少钱
How much time
多少时间
How much emotion
多少感情
Pretend you're starting from zero
就当从零开始
What would you choose now
你现在会怎么选
If the answer is no
如果答案是不会
Then you know what to do
那你就该知道怎么做了
Second question
第二个问题
The data check
「数据检验」
Don't trust your feelings
不要相信你的感觉
Look at the data
看数据
AI membership
AI会员
How many times did you open it in the past 30 days
过去30天你打开了几次
Not how many times you plan to use it
不是你打算用
But how many times you actually used it
是你真的用了
Open your screen time
打开屏幕使用时间
Numbers don't lie
数字不骗人
Stocks
股票
What's your stop-loss line
你的止损线是多少
Has it been hit
到了吗
Job
工作
Did you learn anything new in the past year
过去一年你学到新东西了吗
Did you get a raise
涨薪了吗
Replace feeling okay with letting data decide
把感觉还行变成数据说了算
And sunk cost can't fool you anymore
沉没成本就骗不了你了
Third question
第三个问题
Opportunity cost
「机会成本」
There's another term in economics
经济学里还有一个词
Called opportunity cost
叫机会成本
When you choose A
你选了A
You lose the opportunity to do B
就失去了做B的机会
The same money
同样这笔钱
This time
这些时间
This energy
这些精力
If not spent here
如果不花在这里
What else could you do with it
你还能做什么
Maybe that 200 yuan AI membership fee
也许那200块AI会员费
Spent on another tool could double your ROI
花在另一个工具上ROI翻倍
Maybe the energy drained by this relationship
也许这段感情消耗的精力
Would be better spent improving yourself
用来提升自己更值
Maybe that extra year you stuck around at this company
也许你在这家公司多熬的一年
Made you miss a better opportunity window
刚好错过了一个更好的机会窗口
Sunk cost keeps you focused on what you've already spent
沉没成本让你只盯着过去花了什么
Opportunity cost reminds you what you could still gain
机会成本提醒你未来还能得到什么
Use them together
这两个一起用
And it becomes very hard to make irrational decisions
你就很难再做出不理性的决策了
Let me walk you through a scenario
我给你模拟一个场景
You have an AI membership
你有一个AI会员
200 yuan per month
每月200块
You've renewed for 8 months already
已经续了8个月了
Now you need to decide
你现在要决定
Whether to keep it
要不要继续
Apply the zero-based test
用归零测试
Imagine seeing this tool for the first time today
假设今天第一次看到这个工具
Would you spend 200 yuan on it
你会花200块买吗
You think about it probably not
你想了想……好像不会
Apply the data check
用数据检验
How many times did you open it in the past 30 days
过去30天你打开了几次
Twice
2次
Less than 10 minutes each time
每次不到10分钟
Apply opportunity cost
用机会成本
If you save this 200 yuan
这200块如果省下来
That's 2400 a year
一年2400
Enough to buy a tool you actually use every day
够你买一个你真正天天在用的工具了
After running through all three methods
三个方法一过
The answer is crystal clear
答案清清楚楚
Cancel
取消
By the way
对了
After watching this video today
今天看完这个视频
I suggest you do one thing immediately
我建议你立刻做一件事
Open your phone's subscription list
打开你手机的订阅列表
Run every membership through the zero-based test
把每一个会员用归零测试过一遍
Imagine you're seeing each tool for the first time today
假设你今天才第一次看到这个工具
Would you still spend money on it
你还会花钱买吗
Anything you hesitate on for more than 3 seconds
凡是你犹豫超过3秒的
Cancel immediately
直接取消
Don't think about what if I need it next month
不要想万一下个月要用
When you actually need it next month
下个月真要用的时候
Just buy it then
再买就是了
Every yuan you save today
你今天省下来的每一块钱
Is a raise you give yourself
都是你给自己的加薪
The core essence of sunk cost comes down to one sentence
其实沉没成本最核心的本质就一句话
Things in the past
过去的事
Are not within your power to change
不是你能改变的
But things in the future
但未来的事
Are entirely within your power to choose
全是你能选择的
When you truly understand this
当你真正理解这一点
You'll find that many decisions you've agonized over
你会发现很多纠结了很久的决定
The answer has been clear all along
答案其实一直很清楚
You just needed a reason
你只是需要一个理由
To let go
让自己放手
This video today
今天这个视频
Is that reason
就是这个理由
Finally
最后
Let me leave you with one thought
送你一句话
Truly smart people
真正聪明的人
Aren't those who never make mistakes
不是从不犯错
But those who after making mistakes
而是犯了错之后
Don't try to fix them with even bigger mistakes
不会用更大的错来弥补
Money already spent
已经花掉的钱
Let it go
就让它过去
Time already wasted
已经浪费的时间
What matters is
重要的是
Where every next yuan
你接下来的每一块钱
Every next minute
每一分钟
Gets spent
花在哪
If this video helped you
如果你觉得这条视频帮到你了
Drop a follow
点个关注
I tell one economics story every week
我每周讲一个经济学故事
Helping you see through the mental traps
帮你看透那些你每天都在踩
You step into every day but never notice
但从来没注意到的思维陷阱
Next episode
下一期
We'll talk about why AI companies are giving things away for free
我们聊聊为什么AI公司都在免费送你东西
What's their real calculation
他们到底在算什么账
See you next time
我们下期见